Guide to the John Gunther Papers 1935-1967
University of Chicago Library
Gunther, John. Papers
1935-1967
61 linear feet (122 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
John Gunther, journalist and writer. The John Gunther Papers consist of different draft versions of Gunther's books along with correspondence, articles, and notes related to these projects. Papers related to Chicago Revisited.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
John Gunther, the internationally known journalist and writer, was born in 1901 in Chicago. He was educated in the public schools there and graduated from the University of Chicago in 1922, where he had been literary editor of the Daily Maroon, the campus newspaper. Soon after graduation he began work as a foreign correspondent for the Chicago Daily News and remained in Europe until 1936. He was at various times in charge of Daily News offices in London, Berlin, Vienna, Moscow, Rome, and Paris, and has worked or visited in every European country except Portugal. In 1936, he published the results of his early years of European experience in the first of his "inside" books, INSIDE EUROPE, which sold more than 500,000 copies.
For more than twenty years Gunther continued the writing of these phenomenally successful "inside" books which include INSIDE ASIA (1939), INSIDE LATIN AMERICA (1941), INSIDE U.S.A. (1947), INSIDE AFRICA (1955), INSIDE RUSSIA TODAY (1958), and most recently INSIDE EUROPE TODAY (1961). In addition, Gunther wrote a number of other books on current affairs as well as biographical studies of major figures in American life. These include D-DAY (1944), concerning the Allied invasion of Italy and the Mediterranean war in general; BEHIND THE CURTAIN (1949), investigating conditions in Europe at the time, especially the countries behind the Iron Curtain; ROOSEVELT IN RETROSPECT (1950); THE RIDDLE OF MACARTHUR (1951); EISENHOWER: THE MAN AND THE SYMBOL (1952); TAKEN AT THE FLOOD: THE STORY OF ALBERT D. LASKER (1960). In 1949, Gunther published the deeply moving account of the death of his young son, John, two years earlier, of a brain tumor, entitled DEATH BE NOT PROUD. In addition, he is the author of a series of juvenile books, which are revised versions for younger readers of chapters from INSIDE AFRICA and INSIDE RUSSIA TODAY. He has also written three other children's books on historical and mythical characters: ALEXANDER THE GREAT (1952), JULIUS CAESAR (1959), and THE GOLDEN FLEECE (1959). In 1955, Gunther prepared the text and captions for DAYS TO REMEMBER, a pictorial volume on America, 1945-1955, written in collaboration with Bernard Quint, associate art editor of Life.
Scope Note
When the papers were deposited, they included all of the material used by Gunther in preparing his manuscripts. Much of this material was discarded. This included numerous clippings, generally from well-known publications, newspapers such as The New York Times, the New York Herald-Tribune, the Chicago Daily News, The Times (London), the Manchester Guardian, magazines such as the New Statesman, The Nation, Time, Life, Foreign Affairs, The New Republic, Colliers, and Foreign Policy Reports. Also included were government documents and press releases, United Nations documents, pamphlets, both tourist-type and informational issued by official agencies and private organizations, and reprints of articles. The collection also contained numerous bibliographical notes which referred to page or volume in some published work. There were also cryptic notes, apparently reminders to the author to relate some anecdote or to include some point of fact. Also discarded were unmarked copies of manuscripts and unmarked galley proofs. The materials retained in the collection were those manuscripts and notes which showed most clearly Gunther's methods and sources of information. Gunther has described his work methods in two articles published in Harper's Magazine, March and April, 1961, entitled "The Fun of Writing the Inside Books," and in a longer book version of these articles published in 1962 entitled A Fragment of Autobiography.
The collection includes notes, manuscripts and proofs in various stages and correspondence dealing with Gunther's works. The material in the collection can be subdivided under several headings: manuscripts, correspondence, notes, and miscellaneous materials.
The manuscripts include the original manuscripts for all of Gunther's works. These are generally rough typewritten drafts, done by Gunther himself. They are heavily corrected with both major stylistic and substantive changes. Most of these revisions are in longhand, but Gunther also used the "cut and paste" method to rearrange paragraphs and phrases. Once this first attempt was in reasonably acceptable order, the first formal typing was done by a typist. Gunther then heavily revised this typewritten draft in the same manner described above. This is the First Revision or Second Draft of the manuscript. Occasionally there are three drafts of some chapters. Again the complete manuscript with these new revisions was typed and this clean copy revised. This Third or last Draft, called "the Printer's Copy," was not so heavily revised, but even so, there are usually a dozen cuts and changes, mostly to change "verbal felicities," (Gunther's phrase) on every page. The book was set in type from this copy. (If there had been no time to completely retype the First Revision, only those pages or fragments of pages which were heavily revised were retyped and inserted to make up the Printer's Copy.) Also included are the original manuscripts of Gunther's articles for magazines or newspapers, portions of which were sometimes included in the published books in revised form, and news dispatches which Gunther often wrote while on his various trips.
For several of Gunther's works, carbon copies of the original manuscript were sent to readers for correction or checking. Those sections which were annotated by Gunther's "experts" or specialists also make up part of the collection and are clearly indicated.
Galley proofs could be called the Fourth Draft, since Gunther revised them completely, mostly for stylistic reasons, but also to bring the book up to date by adding new material about persons or events.
The correspondence concerning the "inside" books, which is not an extensive part of the papers thus far deposited, has been divided into two sections. Informational and Post-publication. The "Informational" correspondence concerns questions of fact, answers to Gunther's inquiries, comments on manuscripts sent to "experts," material bringing Gunther up to date, suggestions from friends and acquaintances of people to see, etc. The "Post-publication" correspondence is from readers who commented on Gunther's works. Post-publication letters from well-known persons and from people who had corresponded with Gunther before publication are generally included in the Informational file. The correspondence is filed with the manuscripts and notes for the book with which it is concerned. However, there are two additional boxes of correspondence which include material concerning Gunther's publishers, Harper and Bros, and Hamish Hamilton, and some folders of miscellaneous correspondence which do not deal with specific books.
The notes constitute the major portion of the collection to date. Gunther wrote his notes longhand on small scratch pads. The great majority of these notes are interview notes, some from well-known persons in government, business or the arts, others with the average citizen, such as taxi cab drivers or the like. Others are notes taken at lunches, dinners, or parties. Generally, these notes are identified by the last name of the person interviewed, but sometimes they are simply marked "embassy," or "lunch," indicating that the notes were taken at an embassy meeting or affair, or at a luncheon party, or they are marked with the first name, the initials, or perhaps the nickname of the person interviewed. Gunther clipped all of his interview notes apart into thousand of little "sniblets" which were carefully subdivided into topics. He was generally very careful when cutting the notes apart to indicate the interviewee. In arranging these notes, however, they have been drawn together by the name of the person interviewed. Where possible, from internal evidence, from the published works, from Gunther's agendas of persons to see, they have been identified. Many, however, are not, and are simply listed under the last name on the guide or by Gunther's own designation.
The miscellaneous notes include a wide variety of material. Many are unmarked notes, which are generally Gunther's impressions of someone, someplace or some event. These have been filed by topic. Other notes are sentences, phrases, or paragraphs, which Gunther jotted down and which were subsequently used in the manuscript in some form or another. Also included are outlines for his chapters, names of persons to see or interview, itineraries, schedules, and agendas, as well as check sheets, proof sheets, libel sheets, and watch sheets. These latter were made by Gunther to determine the accuracy of his manuscript after rereading.
The miscellaneous materials section is made up of articles, memoranda, news dispatches and notes by other persons. In some countries, Gunther would commission someone on the local scene to prepare information papers. News dispatches, articles, and other memoranda, both published and unpublished, sent to Gunther by his colleagues and some of his contacts are included in this designation.
The collection is in 122 boxes. A guide to the material follows. The manuscripts are arranged by book publication date, beginning with INSIDE EUROPE. Preceding the guide to each book, there is a more detailed description of the material in each section. The juvenile books, correspondence, and materials from CHICAGO REVISTED are located at the end of the guide.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Gunther, John, 1929-1947; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Lasker, Albert Davis, 1880-1952; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; University of Chicago; Cancer -- Patients -- Biography; Eastern question; Eastern question (Far East); Propaganda, German; Teenagers-Diseases; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945-Mediterranean Sea; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- France -- Normandy; Journalists -- Correspondence; Journalists -- Biography; Statesmen; Africa -- Description and travel; Asia -- Biography; Asia -- Politics and government; Brazil -- Politics and government -- 1930-1945; Europe -- Description and travel -- 1945-; Europe -- Kings and rulers; Europe -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Europe, Central-Politics and government; Japan -- History -- Allied occupation, 1945-1952; Latin America -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Latin America -- Description and travel; Soviet Union; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1991; United States -- Description and travel
INVENTORY
- Series I: Inside Europe
  INSIDE EUROPE, published in 1936, is the first of the "inside books." The papers are contained in seven boxes. With the exception of the chapters on Germany, there is only one complete revision of this material. The chapters on Germany, however, have two or three drafts. These additional drafts have been included with the original manuscript and have been so marked. The manuscripts, therefore, are as follows-
  1. Original manuscript, including the additional drafts on Germany
  2. First Revision (Second Draft) which is a typed copy of the original manuscript, and is substantially the same as the published version; and
  3. Galley proofs, with the author's corrections and additions.
  The Printer's Copy was not included in the original deposit.
  There were five editions of INSIDE EUROPE. The second edition (October, 1936) did not necessitate the setting up of new type, but merely required insertions. The manuscript inserts must be used with the pagination of the first edition. New chapters were also added. These manuscripts are found with the "Revised Edition." However, the last two editions, the New 1938 Edition and the 1940 War Edition, were complete reworkings of the book, including new typesetting. The pages of one of the published editions were pasted onto large sheets of paper and Gunther made his corrections on the pages themselves and in the margins. The original manuscripts of inserts and the new chapters are clearly indicated. In October 1938, there was another edition, entitled the Peace Edition, which included mainly a new introduction and one new chapter, entitled "The Fascist Offensive," which was inserted in the book as Chapter 7a. Galley proofs of the revisions are not included in the collection.
  Manuscripts of twenty-one articles written by Gunther are also part of the papers. Most appeared in such magazines as Harpers, The Nation, and Foreign Affairs. They deal with a wide variety of subjects and have been listed alphabetically. Most are simply carbon copies of the manuscript. Several of the articles, or portions of them, were used in the published book, but only after being heavily revised. There are also press dispatches from the Balkans written by Gunther, and miscellaneous typewritten notes, mostly on Austria, where Gunther had been stationed for many years.
  The correspondence concerning this book is not extensive. One folder contains several letters from U.S. Embassy officials in Rome, London, Prague, and Berlin which answer questions of fact posed by Gunther. There are also several letters from reporters answering certain of Gunther's questions. The post-publication letters came mostly from English readers generally pointing out minor errors of fact.
  The research notes for INSIDE EUROPE are not as voluminous as those for some of Gunther's other books. He was, of course, much more intimately informed on European affairs, since he had spent eleven years in Europe as a foreign correspondent. There are some interview notes, particularly those on a talk with Thomas Masaryk, founder and first president of Czechoslovakia, several English politicians, and H. R. Knickerbocker, the well-informed American journalist. Most of the notes, arranged alphabetically by country and topic, are factual notes.
  Among miscellaneous materials are articles, memoranda, and copies of dispatches by several of Gunther's colleagues.
  - Subseries 1: Original Manuscript
    - Preliminary Title Page, Dedication, Table of Contents, Prefatory Note (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 1 Hitler (1st draft) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 1 Hitler: Character (2nd draft) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 1 Hitler (3rd draft) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 2 Path to Aryan Glory (1st draft, pp. 1-16) Chapter 2 Hitler, Origins (2nd draft) Chapter 2 Psychopathology of Dictators (3rd draft) Chapter 2 Path to Aryan Glory (1st draft, pp. 17-29) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 3 Who Killed the German Republic? (2nd draft) Chapter 3 Who Killed the German Republic? (3rd draft) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 3 The Trick by Fire and the Purge by Blood (1st draft) Chapter 4 The Trick by Fire and the Purge by Blood (2nd draft) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 4 All the Little Hitlers (1st draft) Chapter 5 The Two G-Men (2nd draft) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 6 The Other Little Hitlers (2nd draft) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 5 War, Peace, Policy, and Cash (1st draft) Chapter 7 War, Peace, Policy, and Cash (2nd draft) Chapter 7 War, Peace, Policy, and Cash (3rd draft) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 8 "Lavaluation" Chapter 9 French Policy-and Why? (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 10 More About Frenchmen Chapter 11 Fascism in France? (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 12 Interlude in Spain (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 13 Mussolini Chapter 14 Who Else in Italy? Chapter 15 War in Abyssinia (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 16 England, The Ruling Classes Chapter 17 Baldwin (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 18 Men of Whitehall Chapter 19 Left and Right in England (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 20 Danube Blues Chapter 21 The February Tragedy (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 22 Death of Dollfuss Chapter 23 Austria Infelix (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 24 Dr. Otto Hapsburg and Gen. Julius Goemboes Chapter 25 Masaryk and Benes (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 26 The Lupescu Comedy Chapter 27 Jugoslavia after Alexander (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 28 Balkan Kings Chapter 29 The Turkish Colossus Chapter 30 Poland Without Pilsudski Chapter 31 Half a League Onward (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 30 Stalin Chapter 31 Men Around Stalin (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 32 "Duranty's Inferno" Acknowledgements and Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: First Revision (Second Draft)
    - Chapter 1 Hitler Chapter 2 Psychopathology of Dictators (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 3 Who Killed the German Republic? Chapter 4 The Trick by Fire and the Purge by Blood (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 5 The Two G-Men Chapter 6 The Other Little Hitlers (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 7 War, Peace, Policy, and Cash Chapter 8 "Lavaluation" (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 9 French Policy-and Why Chapter 10 More About Frenchmen (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 11 Fascism in France Chapter 12 Interlude in Spain (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 13 Mussolini Chapter 14 Who Else in Italy? Chapter 15 War in Abyssinia (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 16 England, The Ruling Class Chapter 17 Baldwin Chapter 18 Men of Whitehall (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 19 Left and Right in England Chapter 20 Danube Blues Chapter 21 The February Tragedy (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 22 Death of Dollfuss Chapter 23 Austria Infelix Chapter 24 Dr. Otto Hapsburg and General Julius Goemboes (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 25 Masaryk and Benes Chapter 26 The Lupescu Comedy Chapter 27 Jugoslavia after Alexander (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 28 Balkan Kings Chapter 29 The Turkish Colossus Chapter 30 Poland Without Pilsudski Chapter 31 Half a League Onward (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Chapter 32 Stalin Chapter 33 Men Around Stalin (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 3: Galley Proofs
    - Chapters 1-4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 5-7 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 8-11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Chapters 12-15 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chapters 16-19 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Chapters 20-23 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Chapters 24-27 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Chapters 28-31 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Chapters 32-34 Acknowledgments and Bibliography (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 4: Revised Edition (October 1936)
    - Inserts-general (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 8 Leon Blum Chapter 20 Eamon de Valera Chapter 17 Abdication of Edward VIII (February, 1937) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 5: New 1938 Edition (November 1937)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapters 1-11 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapters 12-21 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapters 22-33 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapters 34-38, and final corrections (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Original manuscript-New Chapter 12-The Spanish Civil War (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Original manuscript-New Chapter 18-Chamberlain and Baldwin (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Original manuscript-New Chapter 32-The Notable Neutrals (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Original manuscript-New Chapter 35-The Russian Trials (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 6: Peace Edition (October 1938)
    - Original manuscript-New Introduction Original manuscript-New Chapter 7a-The Fascist Offensive (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Subseries 7: 1940 War Edition
    - Original manuscript of inserts (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Preface, Introduction, Bibliographical note (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 1 Hitler Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 2 Psychopathology of Dictators (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 3 Who Killed the German Republic Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 4 The Trick by Fire and the Purge by Blood Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 5 The Two G-Men (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 6 The Other Little Hitlers Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 7 War, Peace, Policy, and Cash (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 8 The Fascist Offensive Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 9 From Munich to Warsaw (new) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 10 Daladier (new) and Blum Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 11 French Policy-And Why (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 12 More About Frenchmen Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 13 Fascism and the Front Populaire (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 14 The Spanish Civil War (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 15 Mussolini Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 16 Who Else in Italy? Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 17 War in Abyssinia (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 18 England, The Ruling Classes Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 19 The Abdication Crisis Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 20 Chamberlain, Baldwin, and Churchill (new) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 21 Men of Whitehall Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 22 Left and Right in England (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Page revisions (with inserts) -Chapter 23 De Valera Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 24 The February Tragedy Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 25 Danube Blues (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 26 Death of Dollfuss Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 27 Austria Infelix Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 28 Hungary and Dr. Hapsburg (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 29 Masaryk and Benes Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 30 Carol, Lupescu, and Rumania (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 31 Jugoslavia after Alexander Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 32 Balkan Kings Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 33 The Turkish Colossus (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 34 Poland and the Baltic States Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 35 The Notable Neutrals Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 36 Half a League Onward (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 37 Stalin Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 38 Men Around Stalin (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 39 The Russian Trials Page revisions (with inserts)-Chapter 40 "Duranty's Inferno" (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 8: Published Articles by Gunther
    - After the Dollfuss Murder Arson Deluxe Austria, Hot on the Griddle (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - The Austrian Struggle for Power The Authority Complex (incomplete) Balkan Kings Bigger and Better Wars (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Counter Revolution Austrian Style Dollfuss and the Future of Austria Eight Questions about Hitler The Fascist Regime is Austria The Fire-Still Burning The Hapsburg Question (incomplete) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Hapsburg's Otto (incomplete) Has Hitler an Oedipus Complex (incomplete) The Nazi Tamer of Lions Policy by Murder (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Slaughter for Sale (original manuscript) The Slaughter in Austria This Other Eden What Alfonso Left Behind Press Dispatches from Balkans (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 9: Memoranda
    - Notes on Dollfuss and Austria Situation Notes on Hitler Notes on Baldwin Notes on Schutzbund Trial Notes on Vienna and Austria (Box 5, Folder 13)